I am going to talk about myself,
سأتحدث عن نفسي
which I rarely do, because I --
وذلك أمرًا يحدث نادرًا
well for one thing, I prefer to talk about things I know nothing about.
أولا لأني أفضل الحديث عن الأشياء التي لا أعرف شيئا عنها
And secondly, I'm a recovering narcissist.
وثانيًا أنا نرجسية في طور الشفاء
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I didn't know I was a narcissist actually.
في الحقيقة لم أعرف أني نرجسية
I thought narcissism meant you loved yourself.
ظننت النرجسية هي حبك لذاتك
And then someone told me there is a flip side to it.
ثم أخبرني أحدهم عن وجود جانب آخر لها
So it's actually drearier than self-love;
لذا إن الأمر يتعدى حب الذات
it's unrequited self-love.
إنه حب غير متبادل للذات
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I don't feel I can afford a relapse.
لا أظن أن بإمكاني تحمل الإنتكاس
But I want to, though, explain
ولكني أريد أن أشرح عن
how I came to design my own particular brand of comedy
كيف صممت بصمتي في الكوميديا
because I've been through so many different forms of it.
لأني جربت أشكال كثيرة من الكوميديا
I started with improvisation,
بدأت بالإرتجال
in a particular form of improvisation called theater games,
بإحدى أنواعها وهو الألعاب المسرحية
which had one rule,
والتي تحكمها قاعدة واحدة
which I always thought was a great rule for an ethic for a society.
برأيي تعتبر رائعة لأخلاقيات المجتمع
And the rule was, you couldn't deny the other person's reality,
وهي تتمثل في عدم قدرتك إنكار واقع الآخر
you could only build on it.
بإمكانك فقط البناء عليه
And of course we live in a society that's all about
وبالطبع نحن نعيش في مجتمع يدور حول
contradicting other peoples' reality.
مناقضة واقع الآخرين
It's all about contradiction,
إنه ليس سوى تناقض
which I think is why I'm so sensitive to contradiction in general.
ولهذا السبب أعتقد أني مفرطة الحساسية تجاه التناقض عاموماً
I see it everywhere.
أرى التناقض في كل مكان
Like polls. You know, it's always curious to me
مثل الإستطلاعات تثير دائما فضولي
that in public opinion polls
وبالأخص استطلاعات الرأي العام
the percentage of Americans who don't know the answer to any given question
إن نسبة الأمريكان الذين لا يعرفون أي جواب لأي سؤال
is always two percent.
هي دائما 2 بالمئة
75 percent of Americans
75 بالمئة من الأمريكان
think Alaska is part of Canada.
يعتقدون أن آلاسكا هي جزء من كندا
But only two percent don't know the effect
وفي المقابل 2 بالمئة لا يعرفون عن
that the debacle in Argentina will have on the IMF's monetary policy --
أثر إنهيار اقتصاد الأرجنتين في صندوق النقد الدولي
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
seems a contradiction.
تبدو لي كتناقض.
Or this ad that I read in the New York Times:
أو هذا الإعلان قرأته في صحيفة نيويورك تايمز:
"Wearing a fine watch speaks loudly of your rank in society.
"ارتداؤك ساعة فاخرة تنطق عالياً بمكاتنك في المجتمع.
Buying it from us screams good taste."
شراؤك منا يصرخ بالمذاق الجيد."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Or this that I found in a magazine called California Lawyer,
أو هذا ما وجدته في مجلة تسمى محامي كاليفورنيا،
in an article that is surely meant for the lawyers at Enron.
في مقال يقصد بلاشك المحامين في انرون.
"Surviving the Slammer: Do's and Don'ts."
"النجاة من السجن . ما يُفعل وما يُترك."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"Don't use big words."
" عدم استخدام الكلمات الكبيرة"
"Learn the lingua franca."
"تعلم لغة مشتركة".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Yeah. "Lingua this, Frankie."
نعم. هذا لسان فرانكي.
And I suppose it's a contradiction that I
وأنا أفترض أنه من التناقض أنني
talk about science when I don't know math.
أتحدث عن العلم وأنا أجهل الرياضيات
You know, because -- and by the way to I was so grateful to Dean Kamen
كما تعلمون ، لأنه -- وبالمناسبة كنت ممتنة لذلك للعميد كامين
for pointing out that one of the reasons,
لافتاً الى أن واحداً من الأسباب،
that there are cultural reasons
أن هناك أسباب ثقافية
that women and minorities don't enter the fields of science and technology --
أن النساء والأقليات لا تدخل في مجالات العلوم والتكنولوجيا --
because for instance, the reason I don't do math is,
لأنه على سبيل المثال، والسبب أنني لا آتقن الرياضيات،
I was taught to do math and read at the same time.
تعلمت الرياضيات والقراءة في الوقت نفسه.
So you're six years old, you're reading Snow White and the Seven Dwarves,
لذلك أنت فعمر الست سنوات، تقرأ سنو وايت والأقزام السبعة
and it becomes rapidly obvious
أصبح واضحاً بشكل سريع
that there are only two kinds of men in the world:
هناك فقط نوعان من الرجال في العالم
dwarves and Prince Charmings.
الأقزام والأمير الساحر
And the odds are seven to one against your finding the prince.
والاحتمالات هي سبعة إلى واحد مقابل العثور على الأمير.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
That's why little girls don't do math. It's too depressing.
هذا هو السبب لمَ الفتيات الصغيرات لا يتقنّ الرياضيات. ذلك محبط جداً.
Of course, by talking about science
بطبيعة الحال، والحديث عن العلم
I also may, as I did the other night,
وأود كما قمت به تلك الليلة
incur the violent wrath of some scientists
تحمل الغضب العنيف من بعض العلماء
who were very upset with me.
الذين كانوا مستائين جدا مني.
I used the word postmodern as if it were OK.
لقد استخدمت كلمة ما بعد الحداثة كما لو كانت فوق موافقة.
And they got very upset.
وقد استاؤا جداً
One of them, to his credit, I think really just wanted to engage me
واحد منهم ، لمصلحته، أعتقد فقط لمجرد أن يشاركني
in a serious argument.
في الجدال الحاد
But I don't engage in serious arguments.
ولكنني لا أنخرط في الجدالات الحادة
I don't approve of them
أنا لا أوافقها
because arguments, of course, are all about contradiction,
لأن الجدالات، وبطبيعة الحال ، تدور حول التناقض.
and they're shaped by the values that I have questions with.
وهي تتشكل من حيث القيم
I have questions with the values of Newtonian science,
لدي تساؤلات حول قيم العلم النيوتوني.
like rationality. You're supposed to be rational in an argument.
مثل العقلانية، ومن المفترض أن يكونوا عقلاء في الحجة.
Well rationality is constructed
كذلك العقلانية هي التي شيدت
by what Christie Hefner was talking about today,
من قبل ما تحدثت عنه كريستي هفنر اليوم،
that mind-body split, you know?
أن إنقسام الرأس والجسم . هل تعلم؟
The head is good, body bad.
الرأس جيد، والجسد سيء.
Head is ego, body id.
الرأس هو الأنا، الجسد معرف
When we say "I," -- as when Rene Descartes said,
وعندما نقول "أنا"-- كما هو الحال عندما قال رينيه ديكارت،
"I think therefore I am," --
" أنا أفكر إذاً أنا موجود"
we mean the head.
نحن هنا نتحدث عن الرأس.
And as David Lee Roth sang in "Just a Gigolo,"
وكما غنى ديفيد لي روث في "راقص محترف فقط"
"I ain't got no body."
" أنا ليس لدي جسد."
That's how you get rationality.
هذه هي الطريقة التي تحصل فيها على العقلانية.
And that's why so much of humor
وهذا السبب أن الكثير من الفكاهة
is the body asserting itself against the head.
هي الجسد الذي يفرض نفسه أمام الرأس
That's why you have toilet humor and sexual humor.
هذا هو السبب لامتلاكك روح الفكاهة والدعابة الجنسية.
That's why you have the Raspyni Brothers
وهذا هو السبب لوجود الأخوين رازبيني
whacking Richard in the genital area.
يصطادون ريتشارد لتضخم في منطقته الحساسة
And we're laughing doubly then
وتضاعفت الضحكات بعدها
because he's the body, but it's also --
والسبب أنه هو الجسد، ولكن أيضاً
Voice offstage: Richard.
صوت الكواليس : ريتشارد.
Emily Levine: Richard. What did I say?
إميلي ليفين : ريتشارد. ماذا أقول؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Richard. Yes but it's also the head,
ريتشارد. نعم لكنه أيضاً الرأس،
the head of the conference.
رئيس المؤتمر.
That's the other way that humor --
هذه الطريقة الأخرى حيث أن النكتة --
like Art Buchwald takes shots at the heads of state.
تشبه فن بوتشوالد في تصوير رؤساء الدول
It doesn't make quite as much money as body humor I'm sure --
الذي لا يصنع الكثير من المال كما تفعل فكاهة الجسد أنا متأكدة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
but nevertheless, what makes us treasure you and adore you.
ولكن مع ذلك، ما يجعلنا نقدركم أنتم ونعشقكم.
There's also a contradiction in rationality in this country though,
ومع ذلك يوجد أيضاً تناقض في العقلانية في هذا البلد
which is, as much as we revere the head,
وهو، بقدر ما نقدس العقل،
we are very anti-intellectual.
نحن نقاوم الفكر بشدة .
I know this because I read in the New York Times,
أنا أعرف هذا لأنني قرأت في صحيفة نيويورك تايمز
the Ayn Rand foundation took out a full-page ad
إعلان خاص مؤسسة أيان راند أخذت صفحة كاملة
after September 11,
بعد أحداث ١١ سبتمبر
in which they said, "The problem is not Iraq or Iran,
حيث قالوا : "المشكلة ليست العراق أو إيران،
the problem in this country, facing this country
المشكلة في هذا البلد أو الذي يواجه هذا البلد
is the university professors and their spawn."
هم أساتذة الجامعة ونسلهم"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So I went back and re-read "The Fountainhead."
فعدت وأعدت قراءة "المنبع".
I don't know how many of you have read it.
أنا لا أعرف كم منكم قد قرأتها
And I'm not an expert on sadomasochism.
وانا لست خبيرة في السادية
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But let me just read you a couple of random passages from page 217.
ولكن دعوني اقرأ عليكم عددا من الفقرات العشوائية من صفحة 217
"The act of a master
"تصرف السيد
taking painful contemptuous possession of her,
يقبض عليها بإزدراء ،
was the kind of rapture she wanted.
كانت نوعا من النشوة التي أرادت.
When they lay together in bed it was,
عندما يستلقيان سويا بالفراش لقد كانت
as it had to be, as the nature of the act demanded,
كما كان لها أن تكون ، كما طلبت طبيعة السيد ،
an act of violence.
فعلاً من العنف.
It was an act of clenched teeth and hatred. It was the unendurable.
كانت من فعل الأسنان المشدودة والكراهية. فقد كانت أمراً لا يحتمل.
Not a caress, but a wave of pain.
ليس عناق، ولكن موجة من الألم.
The agony as an act of passion."
معاناة كمعاناة العاطفة. "
So you can imagine my surprise
لـذلك تستطيعون تصور دهشتي
on reading in The New Yorker
بقراءة جريدة النيويوكر
that Alan Greenspan, Chairman of the Federal Reserve,
أن ألان غرينسبان، رئيس الاحتياطي الفيدرالي ،
claims Ayn Rand as his intellectual mentor.
يطالب آين راند كمرشدته الفكرية
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's like finding out your nanny is a dominatrix.
كإكتشاف أن مربيتك هي المسيطرة
Bad enough we had to see J. Edgar Hoover in a dress.
سئ كفاية كرؤيتنا للإيدجر هوفر في فستان
Now we have to picture Alan Greenspan
الآن لدينا صورة ل(ألان غرينسبان)
in a black leather corset, with a butt tattoo that says,
في مشد اسود من الريش,مع وشم على المؤخرة يقول
"Whip inflation now."
التضخم هو السوط الآن
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And Ayn Rand of course, Ayn Rand
و بالطبع ايان راند, ايان راند
is famous for a philosophy called Objectivism,
المشهور بنظريته (الموضوعية)
which reflects another value of Newtonian physics,
التي تعكس احد قيم الفيزياء النيوتونية
which is objectivity.
و هي الموضوعية
Objectivity basically is constructed
الموضوعية بالاساس مبنية
in that same S&amp;M way.
بطريقة مشابهة لطريقة (s و m )
It's the subject subjugating the object.
ان الفاعل يخضع المفعول به
That's how you assert yourself.
بتلك الطريقة تؤكد نفسك
You make yourself the active voice.
تجعل نفسك الصوت النشط
And the object is the passive no-voice.
و المفعول به هو الصوت الخامل
I was so fascinated by that Oxygen commercial.
انا كنت معجبة بدعاية الاوكسجين تلك
I don't know if you know this but --
انا لا اعلم اذا كنتم تعرفون هذا ولكن --
maybe it's different now, or maybe you were making a statement --
ربما هي مختلفة الان ,أو ربما كنتم تدلون ببيان --
but in many hospital nurseries across the country,
ولكن في العديد من دور الحضانة عبر البلاد
until very recently anyway, according to a book by Jessica Benjamin,
حتى فترة قصيرة, حسب كتاب جيسيكا بنجامين
the signs over the little boys cribs read,
العلامة فوق راس الولد تقول
"I'm a boy,"
"أنا صبي"
and the signs over the little girls cribs read,
و العلامة فوق راس الفتاة تقول
"It's a girl." Yeah.
"إنها فتاة " اجل .
So the passivity was culturally
و بالتالي السلبية من الناحية الثقافية
projected onto the little girls.
مسلطة على الفتيات
And this still goes on as I think I told you last year.
و هذا الشيئ يستمر كما قلت لكم السنة الماضية حسب اعتقدي .
There's a poll that proves --
هناك استطلاع للرأي يثبت --
there was a poll that was given by Time magazine,
كان هناك استطلاع للرأي من مجلة تايم,
in which only men were asked, "Have you ever had sex
الذي يسأل فيه الرجال "هل مارست الجنس يوما
with a woman you actively disliked?"
مع امرأة غير معجب بها "
And well, yeah.
حسنا , نعم
Well, 58 percent said yes,
حسنا , 58 بالمئة أجابو بنعم
which I think is overinflated though
وأنا اعتقد أن هذا أمر مبالغ فيه
because so many men if you just say,
لأن الكثير من الرجال إذا قلت لهم فقط
"Have you ever had sex ... " "Yes!"
"هل مارست الجنس يوما ..." "أجل"
They don't even wait for the rest of it.
حتى انهم لا ينتظرون حتى تكمل البقية
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And of course two percent did not know whether they'd had --
و اثنان بالمئة من الناس لا يعرفون فيما اذا فعلوها ام لا
That's the first callback,
هذا هو الاستدعاء الأول ،
of my attempted quadruple.
من احد الاربعة خاصتي
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So this subject-object thing,
و موضوع الفاعل-المفعول
is part of something I'm very interested in
هو جزء من شئ انا مهتمة به
because this is why, frankly, I believe in political correctness.
ولهذا السبب ,بكل صراحة ,انا اؤمن بالتصحيح السياسي
I do. I think it can go too far.
انا افعل,انا اعتقد انه يمكن ان يذهب بعيدا
I think Ringling Brothers may have gone too far
انا اعتقد ان الاخوة رنجلنج ربما ذهبوا بعيدا
with an ad they took out in the New York Times Magazine.
باعلان اخذوه من مجلة نيويورك تايمز
"We have a lifelong emotional and financial
"نحن نملك حياة مالية عاطفية طويلة
commitment to our Asian Elephant partners."
التزام تجاه اخوتنا الدلافين الاسيوية"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Maybe too far. But you know --
ربما أكثر من اللازم. ولكن كما تعلمون --
I don't think that
لا أعتقد أن
a person of color making fun of white people
شخص ليس من البيض يسخر من الناس البيض
is the same thing as a white person making fun of people of color.
هو الشيء نفسه كشخص من البيض يسخر من أناس ليسو بيضاً (ملونين)
Or women making fun of men is the same as men making fun of women.
أو النساء يسخرن من الرجال هو نفس الشيئ الرجال يسخروا من...
Or poor people making fun of rich people, the same as rich people.
أو الفقراء يسخرون من الأغنياء، والاغنياء كذلك .
I think you can make fun of the have but not the have-nots,
اعتقد انه يمكن أن تسخر ممن هو دونك ولكن ليس العكس،
which is why you don't see me making fun of
ولذلك لن تجدني اسخر من
Kenneth Lay and his charming wife.
كينيث لاي وزوجته الساحرة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
What's funny about being down to four houses?
ما هو مضحك في وصوله الى أربعة منازل؟
And I really learned this lesson
و انا فعلا تعلمت هذا الدرس
during the sex scandals of the Clinton administration or,
من خلال الفضائح الجنسية لادارة كلينتون.
Or as I call them, the good ol' days.
أو كما أسميها، أيام العز.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
When people I knew, you know, people who considered themselves liberal,
عندما أناس انا أعرفهم ,انتم تعرفونهم , يعتبرون انفسهم لبرالين
and everything else,
وكل شيء اخر
were making fun of Jennifer Flowers and Paula Jones.
وكانو يسخرن من زهور جنيفر وبولا جونز
Basically, they were making fun of them for being
أساسا، وكانوا يسخروا منهن لكونهن
trailer trash or white trash.
مقطورة القمامة أو القمامة البيضاء.
It seems, I suppose, a harmless prejudice
على ما يبدو ، على ما أظن ، هو تحيز غير مؤذي
and that you're not really hurting anybody.
وأنك لا تضر أحدا حقا.
Until you read, as I did, an ad in the Los Angeles Times.
حتى تقرأ، كما قرأت، إعلاناً في صحيفة لوس انجلوس.
"For sale: White trash compactor."
"للبيع: ضاغطة قمامة بيضاء
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So this whole subject-object thing
لذا فموضوع الفاعل والمفعول
has relevance to humor in this way.
له علاقة بالفكاهة من هذه الناحية
I read a book by a woman named Amy Richlin,
لقد قرأت كتاب لأمرأة تدعى ايملي ريتشلين
who is the chair of the Classics department at USC.
وهي رئيسة قسم الكلاسيكيات في جامعة جنوب كاليفورنيا.
And the book is called "The Garden of Priapus."
ويسمى كتاب "حديقة القضيب".
And she says that Roman humor
وهي تقول أن الفكاهة الرومانية
mirrors the construction of Roman society.
تعكس بناء المجتمع الروماني
So that Roman society was very top/bottom,
لذا المجتمع الروماني كان قائم على التمييز
as ours is to some degree.
و يشبه مجتمعنا الى درجة ما
And so was humor.
و كذلك كانت الفكاهة
There always had to be the butt of a joke.
كانوا دائما يصلون الى هدف المزحة
So it was always the satirist,
لذا كان دائما الهاجي
like Juvenal or Martial,
مثل جوفينال أو مارشال
represented the audience,
ممثلة للجمهور،
and he was going to make fun of the outsider,
وكان يذهب ليسخر من الخارج
the person who didn't share that subject status.
الشخص الذي لا يشارك وضع الفاعل.
And in stand-up of course,
و بالطبع في حالة الارتجال
the stand-up comedian is supposed to dominate the audience.
الكوميدي المرتجل يجب عليه ان يسيطر على الجمهور
A lot of heckling is the tension
و الكثير من مقاطعة الكلام هو التوتر
of trying to make sure that the
بسبب محاولة التاكد أن
comedian is going to be able to dominate,
الكوميدي قادر على السيطرة
and overcome the heckler.
ويتجاوز المقاطعة
And I got good at that when I was in stand up.
وأنا أكون جيدة عندما أكون أرتجل
But I always hated it because they were
و لكني كرهتهم دائماً لأنهم
dictating the terms of the interaction,
يملون شروط التفاعل
in the same way that engaging in a serious argument
و بنفس الطريقة عند التدخل بمناقشة جدية
determines the content, to some degree,
تحدد المحتوى بدرجة ما
of what you're talking about.
في الموضوع الذي تتكلم به
And I was looking for a form
وأنا كنت ابحث عن نموذج
that didn't have that.
لم يكن يحتوي على ذلك
And so I wanted something that was more interactive.
ولذلك اردت شيئا اكثر تفاعلا
I know that word is so debased now
انا اعرف ان تلك الكلمة محبطة للغاية
by the use of it by Internet marketers.
باستعمالها من قبل مسوقي الانترنت
I really miss the old telemarketers now, I'll tell you that.
انا بجد افتقد المسوّقين القدامى ,ساخبركم بذلك
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I do, because at least there you stood a chance. You know?
انا افعل على الاقل بسبب انك تملك فرصة.هل تعلم؟
I used to actually hang up on them.
لقد اعتدت بالتمسك بهم
But then I read in "Dear Abby" that that was rude.
ولكن فيما بعد قرات في "عزيزتي ابي" انه كان وقحا
So the next time that one called
لذا في المرة القادمة و هذه تدعى
I let him get halfway through his spiel and then I said,
تركته يصل إلى منتصف الطريق من خلال كلامه المعسول وبعدها قلت ،
"You sound sexy."
"تبدو جذاباً "
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
He hung up on me!
تعلْق علي !
But the interactivity allows the audience
لكن التفاعل يسمح للجمهور
to shape what you're going to do as much as
تُشكّل ما كنت تنوي القيام به بقدر
you shape their experience of the world.
ما كنت تشكّل خبرتهم في العالم
And that's really what I'm looking for.
وهذا بالتحديد ما كنت أبحث عنه
And I was sort of, as I was starting to analyze
ولقد كنت نوعاً ما ، كما بدأت التحليل
what exactly it is that I do,
ماذا علي أن أفعل بالضبط
I read a book called "Trickster Makes This World," by Lewis Hyde.
قرأت كتابا بعنوان " الاحتيال يخلق هذا العالم" ، للويس هايد.
And it was like being psychoanalyzed.
وكان كأنه
I mean he had laid it all out.
أعني انه وضع كل شيء.
And then coming to this conference,
وعندها اتى لهذا المؤتمر
I realized that most everybody here
أدركت أن معظمكم هنا
shared those same qualities
اشتركوا بنفس الصفات
because really what trickster is
لأنه حقا الاحتيال هو
is an agent of change.
هو عامل التغير
Trickster is a change agent.
الأحتيال هو عامل التغيير.
And the qualities that I'm about to describe
والصفات التي انا على وشك وصفها
are the qualities that make it possible
هي الصفات التي تجعله ممكناً
to make change happen.
حتي يصبح التغير ممكنناً
And one of these is boundary crossing.
و واحدة من عبور الحدود.
I think this is what so, in fact, infuriated the scientists.
وأعتقد أن هذا هو ما كان الأمر عليه ، في الواقع أثار غضب العلماء.
But I like to cross boundaries.
ولكنّي أود أن أعبر الحدود
I like to, as I said, talk about things I know nothing about.
أود أن ، كما قلت ، الحديث عن أشياء لا أعرف أي شيئ عنها .
(Phone Ringing)
(رنين الهاتف)
I hope that's my agent,
وآمل أن يكون وكيل أعمالي،
because you aren't paying me anything.
لأنكم لا تدفعون لي أي شيء.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I think it's good to talk about things I know nothing about
وأعتقد أنه من الجيد التكلم عن الامور التي لا أعرف أي شيء عنها
because I bring a fresh viewpoint to it, you know?
لأني أحمل وجهة نظر جديدة لأنه، كما تعلمون؟
I'm able to see the contradiction
أصبح قادرة على مشاهدة التناقضات
that you may not be able to see.
التي ما كان لها أن ترى
Like for instance a mime once --
على سبيل المثال الإيماء مرة
or a meme as he called himself.
أو ميمي كما سمى نفسه.
He was a very selfish meme.
لقد كان ميمب أناني جدا
And he said that I had to show more respect
وقال لي أن علي أن أظهر المزيد من الاحترام
because it took up to 18 years
لأن الأمر استغرق ما يصل الى 18 سنة
to learn how to do mime properly.
لأتعلم الأيماء جيداً
And I said, "Well, that's how you know only stupid people go into it."
و أنا أقول ، " حسنا، هكذا يستغرق الأمر وقتاً للأغبياء
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It only takes two years to learn how to talk.
لقد أستغرق سنتان فقط ليتعلم الكلام
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And you know people, this is the problem with
وأنتم تعلمون , هذه المشكلة في
quote, objectivity, unquote.
"الموضوعية "
When you're only surrounded by people
عندما تكون محاطاً بالناس
who speak the same vocabulary as you,
الذين يتحدثون نفس المصطلحات التي تتكلمها ،
or share the same set of assumptions as you,
أو تتشارك معك في نفس المجموعة من الافتراضات ،
you start to think that that's reality.
سوف تبدأ بالأعتقاد أن هذه حقيقة
Like economists, you know, their definition of rational,
مثل الاقتصاديون، كما تعلمون ، تعريفهم للعقلانية ،
that we all act out of our own economic self-interest.
أن نعمل جميعا من منطقتنا الاقتصادية بدافع المصلحة الذاتية.
Well, look at Michael Hawley,
حسنا، أنظر في هاولي مايكل ،
or look at Dean Kamen,
أو انظر إلى دين كومن
or look at my grandmother.
او انظر إلى جدتي
My grandmother always acted in other people's interests,
جدتي عملت دائما في مصلحة الآخرين ،
whether they wanted her to or not.
سواء رغبوا بها أم لا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك )
If they had had an Olympics in martyrdom,
لو كان لديهم أولمبياد في الاستشهاد ،
my grandmother would have lost on purpose.
لكانت جدتي خسرت عنوة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"No, you take the prize.
"انت خذ الجائزة
You're young. I'm old. Who's going to see it?
أنت شابّة أنا عجوز من سيذهب ليراها ؟
Where am I going? I'm going to die soon."
إلى اين انا ذاهبة ؟ انا ذاهبة للموت قريبا "
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So that's one -- this boundary crossing,
لذا هذه واحده -- هذا المعبر الحدودي،
this go-between which --
هذا الانتقال بين الذي --
Fritz Lanting, is that his name,
فريتز لانتنج ،هو أسمه،
actually said that he was a go-between.
وقال انه في الواقع كان وسيط.
That's an actual quality of the trickster.
هذه ميزة حقيقة للمحتالين
And another is, non-oppositional strategies.
والأخرى، عدم معارضة الاستراتيجيات.
And this is instead of contradiction.
وهذا بديل التناقض.
Where you deny the other person's reality,
حيث تنكر واقع الشخص الآخر،
you have paradox
لديك مفارقة
where you allow more than one reality to coexist,
حيث يمكنك السماح للتعايش مع أكثر من حقيقة واحدة،
I think there's another philosophical construction.
أنا أعتقد أنه يوجد بناء فلسفي آخر .
I'm not sure what it's called.
لست متأكدة من أسمه
But my example of it is a sign that I saw in a jewelry store.
ولكن مثالي عليه آرمة رأيتها في محل مجوهرات
It said, "Ears pierced while you wait."
إنها تقول : " أثقب آذانك أثناء إنتظارك"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
There the alternative just boggles the imagination.
هناك البديل يحير الخيال.
"Oh no. Thanks though, I'll leave them here. Thanks very much.
"أوه لا. شكراً، أنا سوف أتركهم هنا . شكراً جزيلاً
I have some errands to run. So I'll be back to pick them up
لدي بعض المهمات لعملها . لذا سأعود لاستلامهم
around five, if that's OK with you.
في حوال الخامسة ، أذا كان هذا ممكن معك
Huh? Huh? What? Can't hear you."
هاه؟ هاه؟ ماذا؟ لا يمكن أن نسمع لكم ".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And another attribute of the trickster
وخصلة أخرى للمحتالين
is smart luck.
أنه الحظ الذكي
That accidents, that Louis Kahn, who talked about accidents,
هذه الصدف، التي تكلم عنها لويس خان عنها
this is another quality of the trickster.
هي ميزة أخرى للمحتالين .
The trickster has a mind that is prepared for the unprepared.
المحتال لديه عقل مستعد للاتحضير
That, and I will say this to the scientists,
هذا، وأنا أقول هذا للعلماء،
that the trickster has the ability to hold
أن المحتال لديه القدرة على حمل
his ideas lightly
أفكاره بخفة
so that he can let room in for new ideas
حتى يتمكن من ترك الغرفة في البحث عن أفكار جديدة
or to see the contradictions or the hidden problems
أو ليرى التناقضات أو المشاكل المخفية
with his ideas.
مع هذه الافكار
I had no joke for that.
لم يكن لدي أي نكتة لذلك.
I just wanted to put the scientists in their place.
أردت فقط أن يوضع العلماء في مكانهم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But here's how I think I like to make change,
ولكن أليك كيف أفكر ، انا أحب أن اصنع التغير
and that is in making connections.
وذلك عبر تفعيل الاتصالات.
This is what I tend to see
هذا ما أميل إلى رؤيتة
almost more than contradictions.
تقريبا أكثر من التناقضات.
Like the, what do you call those toes of the gecko?
مثل، ما تسمون هذه أصابع الوزغة؟
You know, the toes of the gecko,
تعلمون ، فإن أصابع الوزغة (أبو بريص)،
curling and uncurling like the fingers of Michael Moschen.
مجعدة وغير مجعدة مثل اصابع مايكل موتشين
I love connections.
أحب الاتصالات.
Like I'll read that one of the two attributes
مثل أنا سأقرأ واحدة من سمتين
of matter in the Newtonian universe --
للمادة في نيوتونية الكون (نظرية نيوتن عن الكون )
there are two attributes of matter in the Newtonian universe --
هناك سمتين للمادة في نيوتونية الكون
one is space occupancy. Matter takes up space.
واحدة منهم إشغال الفراغ . المادة تأخذ حيّز
I guess the more you matter the more space you take up,
أنا أعتقد أنه كلما زادت مادتك زاد الحيز الذي تأخذه
which explains the whole SUV phenomenon.
وهو ما يفسر ظاهرة (سيارات الدفع الرباعي) بأكملها.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And the other one though is impenetrability.
والأخرى مع ذلك هي اللااختراقية
Well, in ancient Rome, impenetrability
حسناً ، في روما القديمة ، اللإختراقية
was the criterion of masculinity.
كانت معيار الرجولة
Masculinity depended on you
الرجولة تعتمد عليك
being the active penetrator.
أن تكون مخترقاً فعّال
And then, in economics, there's an active producer
ومن ثم، في الاقتصاد، هناك منتج فعال
and a passive consumer,
ومستهلك سلبي ،
which explains why business always has to
والذي يفسر لماذا ينبغي على الأعمال
penetrate new markets.
إختراق أسواق جديدة.
Well yeah, I mean why we forced China
حسناً أجل ، لماذا أجبرنا الصين
to open her markets.
على فتح أسوقها
And didn't that feel good?
ولم نشعر بالرضى ؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And now we're being penetrated.
والآن نحن نُخترق
You know the biotech companies are actually going inside us
أنتم تعرفون أن شركات التكنلوجيا الحيوية هي في الحقيقة تجري في داخلنا
and planting their little flags on our genes.
وتزرع علاماتها الصغيرة على جيناتنا
You know we're being penetrated.
أنتم تعرفون أنّه يجري إختراقكم
And I suspect, by someone who actively dislikes us.
وأظن أنه من قبل شخص يكرهنا بحق .
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
That's the second of the quadruple.
وهذا الجزء الثاني للرباعيّة
Yes of course you got that. Thank you very much.
نعم بالطبع أستوعبت هذا . شكرا جزيلا.
I still have a way to go.
لا يزال لدي وسيلة للمواصلة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And what I hope to do, when I make these connections,
و ما آمل أن أفعله ، عندما أصنع هذه الروابط،
is short circuit people's thinking.
هو ربط تفكير الناس مثل الدائرة
You know, make you not follow your usual
كما تعلمون ، فأنت لا تتبع طبيعتك
train of association,
بربط العلاقات ،
but make you rewire.
لكنك تجعلك تعيد التوصيل
It literally -- when people say about the shock of recognition,
حرفياً -- عندما يتكلم الناس عن صدمة الاعترف
it's literally re-cognition, rewiring how you think --
انها حرفيا إعادة الإدراك ، إعادة توصيل طريقة تفكيرك
I had a joke to go with this and I forgot it.
كانت لدي نكتة ونسيتها
I'm so sorry. I'm getting like
أنا آسفة ، أصبحت أحب
the woman in that joke about --
المرأة التي في النكتة عن
have you heard this joke about the woman driving with her mother?
هل سمعتم بالنكتة التي تتحدث عن المرأة الت كانت تقود بصحبة والدتها
And the mother is elderly.
والأم كبيرة بالسن
And the mother goes right through a red light.
والأم عبرت خلال الأشارة الحمراء
And the daughter doesn't want to say anything.
والبنت لم ترد أن تقول أي شيئ
She doesn't want to be like, "You're too old to drive."
لم ترد أن تكون مثل ، "أنتي كبيرة جداً على القيادة "
And the mother goes through a second red light.
والأم عبرت مرت عبر الأشارة الحمراء الثانية
And the daughter says, as tactfully as possible,
والبنت قالت بأكثر لباقة ممكنة ،
"Mom, are you aware that you just went through two red lights?"
"أمي ، هل أدركت انك عبرت للتو مرتين خلال الأشارة الحمراء ؟"
And the mother says, "Oh! Am I driving?"
والأم قالت ، " أوه ! هل أنا التي أقود؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And that's the shock of recognition
وهذه هي صدمة الادراك
at the shock of recognition.
عند صدمة الإدراك
That completes the quadruple.
التي تكمل الأربعة أضعاف
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I just want to say two more things.
وأريد أن أقول شيئان آخران للتو .
One is, another characteristic of trickster
الأول هو، سمات أخرى للمحتالين
is that the trickster has to
أن المحتالين عليهم
walk this fine line.
أن يسيروا في هذا الخط للنهاية
He has to have poise.
هو عليه أن يمتلك رباطة جأش
And you know the biggest hurdle for me,
وأنتم تعرفون أكبر عقبة بالنسبة لي ،
in doing what I do,
في فعل ما أفعله،
is constructing my performance
هي في بناء عروضي
so that it's prepared and unprepared.
بحيث انها معدة وغير معدة
Finding the balance between those things
إيجاد التوازن بين هذين الأمرين
is always dangerous
هو شيئ خطير دائماً
because you might tip off too much in the direction of unprepared.
لأنك قد تحذر كثيراً في الاتجاه الغير مستعد فيه .
But being too prepared doesn't leave room
ولكن كونك اكثر استعدادأ لا يترك مجال
for the accidents to happen.
للحوادث أن تحدث .
I was thinking about what Moshe Safdie
كنت أفكر بما قاله موشيه صفيدي
said yesterday about beauty
البارحة عن الجمال
because in his book, Hyde says that
لانه في كتابه , هايدي قالت
sometimes trickster can tip over into beauty.
"بعض المخادعون يمكن أن يعطوا نصائح في الجمال "
But to do that you have to
ولكن لتفعل ذلك عليك
lose all the other qualities
أن تخسر كل الصفات الاخرى
because once you're into beauty
لأنك عندما تكون جميل
you're into a finished thing.
تكون شيء كامل
You're into something that
أنت تكون شيئاً
occupies space and inhabits time.
يحتل مكان و يعيش الوقت .
It's an actual thing.
إنه لشيء فعلي.
And it is always extraordinary to see a thing of beauty.
وإنه لشيئ إستثنائي أن ترى شئ من الجمال .
But if you don't do that,
ولكن اذا لم تفعل ذلك
if you allow for the accident to keep on happening,
أذا سمحت للحادث بالاستمرار
you have the possibility of getting on a wavelength.
لديك الأحتمالية لتكون على الطول الموجي .
I like to think of what I do as a probability wave.
أود أن أفكر في ما أفعله في موجة الاحتمال.
When you go into beauty the probability wave
عندما تدخل في جمال موجة الاحتمال
collapses into one possibility.
تنهار في احتمال واحد
And I like to explore all the possibilities
و انا احب معرفة جميع الاحتمالات
in the hope that you'll be on the wavelength of your audience.
على أمل أن تكونوا على نفس الطول الموجي لجمهوركم
And the one final quality I want to say about trickster is
و الصفة الاخيرة انه
that he doesn't have a home.
لا يملك منزلا
He's always on the road.
هو دائما على الطريق
I want to say to you Richard, in closing,
أريد أن أقول لك ريتشارد ، في الختام ،
that in TED you've created a home.
بأنك في تيد قد صنعت منزلك
And thank you for inviting me into it.
وشكرًا لكم على دعوتكم لي اليها
Thank you very much.
شكرًا جزيلاً
(Applause)
(تصفيق)